<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Infectious Disease | Raunak Shrestha</title>
    <link>/tag/infectious-disease/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/infectious-disease/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Infectious Disease</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Infectious Disease</title>
      <link>/tag/infectious-disease/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting drug-resistant Tuberculosis</title>
      <link>/research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;systems-genomics-modelling-of-drug-resistance-in-mycobacterium-tuberculosis-br&#34;&gt;Systems Genomics Modelling of Drug Resistance in Mycobacterium tuberculosis &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi-drug resistance presents a growing challenge to global tuberculosis (TB) control efforts, with a particularly pressing concern in developing nations where robust disease surveillance and monitoring are lacking. Nepal is one of the countries with a high TB burden. TB is caused by an airborne bacterium, &lt;em&gt;Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/em&gt; (Mtb). Treatment for TB involves antibiotics, however, some Mtb becomes resistant to these drugs, forming drug-resistant TB, which is rapidly increasing and poses a major health threat. The emergence of drug resistance TB is linked to specific mutations in Mtb genome. However, the genetic foundations of drug resistance in TB are not fully understood. The existing catalog of well-characterized Mtb drug-resistant mutations falls short in elucidating numerous instances of drug-resistant TB. Identifying new drug-resistant TB mutations is challenging given the genetic diversity of TB and the complex mechanisms driving the drug resistance. To address these challenges, here, we aim to develop a machine learning method to predict drug-resistant TB leveraging a large pool of TB genomic data. Additionally, we will explore the underlying metabolic adaptation in drug-resistant TB using genome-scale metabolic modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Funded by&lt;/strong&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_rstmh_hu83a0c59349eeaf5bea72ec89d2084b18_18961_199631f53cd8f64ff1492362efd709ba.webp 400w,
               /research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_rstmh_hu83a0c59349eeaf5bea72ec89d2084b18_18961_10c0429c802f201cd05da850ba409d4b.webp 760w,
               /research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_rstmh_hu83a0c59349eeaf5bea72ec89d2084b18_18961_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_rstmh_hu83a0c59349eeaf5bea72ec89d2084b18_18961_199631f53cd8f64ff1492362efd709ba.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;400&#34;
               height=&#34;200&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_nihr_hu5f34ba98764e9c41a855e1ba33bdb9f3_10444_272c14094b892eb67c84fe3c65c6f6a8.webp 400w,
               /research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_nihr_hu5f34ba98764e9c41a855e1ba33bdb9f3_10444_df827dab7c89432ad878f51755f95040.webp 760w,
               /research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_nihr_hu5f34ba98764e9c41a855e1ba33bdb9f3_10444_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research_naamii/tb_drug_resistance/logo_nihr_hu5f34ba98764e9c41a855e1ba33bdb9f3_10444_272c14094b892eb67c84fe3c65c6f6a8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;400&#34;
               height=&#34;200&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing efficient dengue vaccine</title>
      <link>/research_naamii/dengue_vaccine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research_naamii/dengue_vaccine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mining-dengue-virus-immunopeptidome-for-next-generation-dengue-vaccine-br&#34;&gt;Mining Dengue virus immunopeptidome for next-generation dengue vaccine &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dengue is a viral infection caused by the Dengue virus (DENV), transmitted to humans through the bite of infected mosquitoes, particularly female Aedes aegypti and A. albopictus. Dengue presents an escalating global public health crisis, endangering nearly half of the world&amp;rsquo;s population at a significantly high level of risk. Preventing severe dengue cases by vaccination is crucial for reducing the overall disease burden, minimizing hospitalizations, and saving lives. Currently, available dengue vaccines are ineffective in providing complete immunity against all serotypes of the virus, and their efficacy varies widely across different age groups and prior dengue exposure statuses. Thus, there is an urgent need for a balanced dengue vaccine effective against all DENV serotypes. For this, we aim to discover new molecular targets essential for the development of a more effective next-generation dengue vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomic epidemiology to understand virus evolution</title>
      <link>/research_naamii/covid19_genomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research_naamii/covid19_genomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;genomic-epidemiology-of-sars-cov-2-in-nepal&#34;&gt;Genomic epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 in Nepal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), caused by the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) rapidly escalated into a global pandemic. Nepal detected its first case in January 2020, and since then, the country has grappled with over a million infections and a significant loss of life. Throughout the pandemic, scientists have diligently studied the virus&amp;rsquo;s genetic composition and its evolving transmission patterns. Various geographic regions have experienced multiple waves of infection, each dominated by a novel virus variant. Notably, some of these emerging strains pose challenges to the effectiveness of existing vaccines. Understanding these variants, their origins, and their spread within communities is crucial for future pandemic preparedness. In Nepal, researchers have made significant progress by sharing thousands of SARS-CoV-2 genome sequences publicly. However, comprehensive investigation on these cases has not been conducted till date. This study aims to conduct a comprehensive genomic analysis of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in Nepal. We will investigate virus&amp;rsquo;s genetic diversity, evolutionary trajectory, and epidemiological patterns. Our long-term vision is to create bioinformatics pipelines and platforms which could be readily deployed in case of any future epidemics or pandemics which will help us understand the transmission of the infectious disease and enable rapid intervention of the disease. Toward this goal, we have created the “Nepal SARS-CoV-2 Genome Database”, a comprehensive phylogenetic clustering of SARS-CoV-2 genomes from Nepal using Nextstrain, a powerful open-source tool for the real-time interactive visualization of genome sequencing data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
