<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cancer on Raunak Shrestha</title>
    <link>/tags/cancer/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cancer on Raunak Shrestha</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year} Raunak Shrestha</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/cancer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Androgen receptor inhibition increases MHC Class I expression and improves immune response in prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2024_mhc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2024_mhc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Atlas of Accessible Chromatin in Advanced Prostate Cancer Reveals the Epigenetic Evolution during Tumor Progression</title>
      <link>/publication/2024_wcdt_atacseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2024_wcdt_atacseq/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated analyses highlight interactions between the three-dimensional genome and DNA, RNA and epigenomic alterations in metastatic prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2024_wcdt_hic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2024_wcdt_hic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrative analysis of ultra-deep RNA-seq reveals alternative promoter usage as a mechanism of activating oncogenic programmes during prostate cancer progression</title>
      <link>/publication/2024_alternative_promoter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2024_alternative_promoter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HPV-mediated Cancers</title>
      <link>/research_naamii/hpv_cancer_genomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research_naamii/hpv_cancer_genomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;biomarkers-of-hpv-negative-head-and-neck-cancer-br&#34;&gt;Biomarkers of HPV-negative head and neck cancer &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approximately 10% of worldwide cancer cases are linked to viruses. Human papillomavirus (HPV) infection is specifically associated with both cervical cancer and Head and Neck Cancer (HNC), often sexually transmitted. In Nepal, cervical cancer stands out as one of the most commonly diagnosed cancers in women, while HNC ranks as a significant contributor to cancer morbidity in both sexes. HPV infection is identified in nearly all cervical cases. In contrast, about 70% of HNC cases exhibit HPV infections, with the remaining 30% linked to factors such as smoking and alcohol/tobacco consumption, rendering them HPV-negative. The presence or absence of HPV infection in HNC is closely tied to disease prognosis and significantly influences treatment approaches. In cervical cancer and HNC, the virus integrates into the host genome, activating E6/E7 oncoproteins that dysregulate cell-cycle regulation and promote uncontrolled cell proliferation. The risk of HPV-mediated cancers is significantly lowered through HPV vaccination, contributing to a global decrease in its incidence. HPV vaccination campaign globally decreases the prevalence of HPV-positive HNC, leading to a potential increase in HPV-negative HNC in the future. HPV-negative HNC cancers are genetically different than HPV-mediated cancers, often presenting as more advanced disease at the time of diagnosis and less responsive to standard-of-care treatments. Therefore, it is crucial to discern the genomic predictors of HPV-negative cancers that can aid in early detection and disease prognosis prediction. In this study, we will identify genomic predictors of HPV-positive and HPV-negative cancers using machine learning models trained in multi-omics data from both cervical cancer and HNC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The genomic and epigenomic landscape of double-negative metastatic prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2023_dnpc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2023_dnpc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 5-Hydroxymethylcytosine Landscape of Prostate Cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2022_prostate5hmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2022_prostate5hmc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An integrated functional and clinical genomics approach reveals genes driving aggressive metastatic prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2021_prostatecrispr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2021_prostatecrispr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiomics Characterization of Low-grade Serous Ovarian Carcinoma Identifies Potential Biomarkers of MEK-inhibitor Sensitivity and Therapeutic Vulnerability</title>
      <link>/publication/2021_lgsoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2021_lgsoc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autoantibody landscape in patients with advanced prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2020_prostateab/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020_prostateab/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Conserved Evolutionary Trajectories in Tumors</title>
      <link>/publication/2020_conett/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020_conett/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Y-box Binding Protein-1 is Crucial in Acquired Drug Resistance Development in Metastatic Clear-Cell Renal Cell Carcinoma</title>
      <link>/publication/2020_ybox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020_ybox/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Predictive Gene Signature to Guide Precision Oncology of Clear-Cell Renal Cell Carcinoma</title>
      <link>/publication/2020_rcc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020_rcc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pan-cancer Analysis of Whole Genomes</title>
      <link>/publication/2020_pcawg_nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020_pcawg_nature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pathway and network analysis of more than 2,500 whole cancer genomes</title>
      <link>/publication/2020_pcawg_network/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020_pcawg_network/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BAP1 Haploinsufficiency Predicts a Distinct Immunogenic Class of Malignant Peritoneal Mesothelioma</title>
      <link>/publication/2019_mesothelioma/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2019_mesothelioma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial Detection of Conserved Alteration Patterns for Identifying Cancer Subnetworks</title>
      <link>/publication/2019_cdcap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2019_cdcap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HIT&#39;nDRIVE: Patient-Specific Multi-Driver Gene Prioritization for Precision Oncology</title>
      <link>/publication/2017_hitndrive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2017_hitndrive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BIRC6-targeting as potential therapy for advanced, enzalutamide-resistant prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2016_birc6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2016_birc6/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneity in the inter-tumor transcriptome of high risk prostate cancer</title>
      <link>/publication/2014_highriskpca/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2014_highriskpca/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Meta-Analysis Approach for Characterizing Pan-Cancer Mechanisms of Drug Sensitivity in Cell Lines</title>
      <link>/publication/2014_drugresp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2014_drugresp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
